<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in St. Maries in Cambridge, upon Sunday the 27 of March, being the day of His Majesties happy inauguration: By Ri. Holdsvvorth D.D. Master of Emmanuel Colledge in Cambridge, Vicechancellour of the Universitie, and one of His Majesties chaplains. Published by His Majesties command.</title>
            <author>Holdsworth, Richard, 1590-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86449</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2401</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E155_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23312</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871963</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871963</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156852</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86449)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156852)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E155[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in St. Maries in Cambridge, upon Sunday the 27 of March, being the day of His Majesties happy inauguration: By Ri. Holdsvvorth D.D. Master of Emmanuel Colledge in Cambridge, Vicechancellour of the Universitie, and one of His Majesties chaplains. Published by His Majesties command.</title>
                  <author>Holdsworth, Richard, 1590-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Daniel, Printer to the Universitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXLIV, 15 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156852:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156852:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. MARIES IN <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Upon Sunday the 27 of March, being the day of His MAjESTIES happy Inauguration: <hi>By</hi> RI. HOLDSVVORTH D. D. Maſter of <hi>Emmanuel</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Vicechancellour of the Univerſitie, and one of His MAjESTIES Chaplains.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by His MAjESTIES command.</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Roger Daniel,</hi> Printer to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie</hi> of <hi>Cambridge.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:156852:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156852:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTIE CHARLES, By the Grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Gracious Sovereigne,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had not adventured to bring theſe unpoliſhed meditations into the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>light,</hi> much leſſe to have ſet them before the <hi>Sunne,</hi> but that Your Majeſtie was pleaſed to beckon them to Your Self, and to draw them as by Your own beams, ſo under Your own ſhade into Your <hi>Royall Preſence,</hi> that being firſt animated with the gentleneſſe of Your beams, they might not be dazled with the ſplendour. Neither is this the leaſt of Your <hi>Princely excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:156852:3"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth. 8.1.</hi>
               </note> that You pleaſe as Chriſt in the Goſpel, <hi>to come down from the Mount,</hi> for the more free acceſſe of Your people; and know, with <hi>Moſes,</hi> to put the <hi>vail</hi> of <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> over the <hi>ſhinings</hi> of <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> ſo that the meaneſt of Your ſubjects may be refreſht with the <hi>light</hi> of your countenance notwithstanding the <hi>luſtre,</hi> and draw livelihood from the <hi>ſplendour,</hi> through the <hi>ſerenitie,</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the medium of their happineſſe as well as the object to be, under God, in Your Self. It is not to be expected at this preſent, that the irradiations of this light ſhould be ſo vigorous in a cloudy Region: We now ſee to our grief what a miſery it is to have the Royall influence intercepted as of late it hath been, and ſtill is, by thoſe diſastrous obſtructions, which at first had onely the appearance of Elia's cloud,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1. Kings 18.44.</hi>
               </note> like <hi>the hand of a man;</hi> but are ſince grown to that vaſtneſſe, as they threaten to the whole Kingdome ſuch ruine as our ſinnes call for: yet in the midst of theſe ſad diſtractions, it is Your Majesties comfort, that as their occaſions are from below, ſo their diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall is from above, both for the exerciſe of Your Princely <hi>clemency</hi> and <hi>patience,</hi> and for the triall of the <hi>ſincereſt loyaltie</hi> of your ſubjects; yea, and religious hearts, through all theſe clouds, can diſcern, and do with thankfulneſſe acknowledge
<pb facs="tcp:156852:3"/>the ſaying of Solomon to be moſt true,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov. 16.15</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In the light of the Kings countenance there is life:</hi> the life of the whole <hi>State,</hi> that it may happily riſe to the former glory, wherein it ſo long flouriſhed: the life of the <hi>Church,</hi> that it may recover out of this ſad languiſhing condition into which it is brought; the life of the <hi>Univerſities,</hi> that they may fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully spread forth their numerous branches to all parts of the Land: laſtly, the life of this ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable <hi>Tractate</hi> in as many degrees, as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath bestowed it upon man; in that your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie vouchſafed, firſt to require a copie in writing, then to command it to the Preſſe, then to afford it Your Patronage, whileſt it preſenteth to the world ſome little portion of that great happineſse, which this eighteen yeares we have enjoyed, under your bleſſed government. I wiſh the Argument had had a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter workman, but what is defective in the Sermon, ſhall be ſupplied by my prayers, That the <hi>happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> hereafter ſpoken of, howſoever it be now eclips'd, may again ſhine forth in full ſtrength, through Your Majeſties great prudence; whoſe Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all beams as they are powerfull for the fostering of piety, ſo I hope they ſhall be powerfull alſo for the diſpelling of all foggie vapours, that may hazard either to prejudice the welfare of Your people, or
<pb facs="tcp:156852:4"/>to pervert their allegiance. Which as it hath been hitherto untainted, to the envie of other Nations, and honour of our own: So, that it may be alwayes inviolably preſerved, is the daily prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your MAjESTIES humbleſt ſubject and ſervant,
<hi>Ri. Holdſworth.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156852:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALME 144.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Happy is that people that is in ſuch a caſe: yea, happy is that people whoſe God is the <hi>LORD.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Genius of this Scripture, as it is very gracefull and pleaſing in it ſelf, ſo it is alſo very ſuitable to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of this day, on which we are met together. It preſents unto us what we all partake of, if we be ſo well diſpoſed as to ſee it, <hi>Felicitie</hi> or <hi>Happineſſe.</hi> And if a ſingle hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe be too little, behold it is conveyed in two ſtreams; the <hi>ſilver</hi> ſtream, and the <hi>golden.</hi> It is reached forth, as it were, in both the hands of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. There is the happineſſe of the left hand, which is <hi>Civill,</hi> in the firſt clauſe of the words; and the happineſſe of the right, which is <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Religious,</hi> in the ſecond. Anſwerable to theſe are the two welcome aſpects of this day: the <hi>Civill</hi> aſpect or reference, which ariſeth from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall revolution, as it is <hi>Dies Principis,</hi> a day of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie for the honour of the King: and the <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi> aſpect from the weekly revolution, as it is <hi>Dies Dominica,</hi> a day of devotion for the worſhip of God. In theſe there is ſo evident a correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that I cannot but congratulate, both the day to the text, and the text to the day, in regard
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156852:5"/>of their mutuall complications. For we have, on the one ſide, both clauſes of the text in the day: and on the other, both references of the day in the text. <hi>Happineſſe</hi> is the language of all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and, that which addes to the contentment, it is Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with an Echo, or ingemination; <hi>Happy</hi> and <hi>Happy.</hi> From this ingemination ariſe the parts of the text; the ſame which are the parts both of the greater world and the leſſe. As the heaven and earth in the one, and the body and the ſoul in the other: ſo are the paſſages of this Scripture in the two veins of Happineſſe. We may range them as Iſaac doth the two parts of his bleſſing, Gen. 27. The vein of civill happineſſe,
<note place="margin">Gen. 27.28.</note> in <hi>the fatneſſe of the earth:</hi> and the vein of Divine happineſſe, in <hi>the dew of heaven.</hi> Or (if you will have it out of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel) here's Marthaes portion in the <hi>many things</hi> of the body:
<note place="margin">Luke 10.41, 42</note> and Maries better part in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num neceſſarium</hi> of the ſoul. To give it yet more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely, here's the path of <hi>Proſperity</hi> in Outward comforts, <hi>Happy is the people that is in ſuch a caſe:</hi> and the path of <hi>Piety</hi> in comforts Spirituall; <hi>Yea, happy is that people which have the</hi> LORD <hi>for their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of the firſt, without any further ſubdiviſion, I will onely ſhew what it is the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt treats of: and that ſhall be, by way of Grada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in theſe three particulars. It is <hi>De</hi> FELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CITATE; <hi>De Felicitate</hi> POPULI; <hi>De</hi> HAC <hi>felicitate populi:</hi> Of <hi>happineſſe;</hi> Of the <hi>peoples</hi> happineſſe; Of the peoples happineſſe, as <hi>in ſuch a caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:156852:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Happineſſe</hi> is the generall, and the firſt: a noble argument, and worthy of an inſpired pen, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Pſalmiſts. Of all other there can be none better to ſpeak of <hi>popular</hi> happineſſe, then ſuch a <hi>King:</hi> nor of <hi>celeſtiall,</hi> then ſuch a <hi>Prophet.</hi> Yet I mean not to diſcourſe of it in the full latitude, but onely as it hath a peculiar poſiture in this Pſalme, very various and different from the order of other Pſalmes. In this Pſalme it is reſerved to the <hi>end,</hi> as the cloſe of the foregoing meditations: In other Pſalmes it is ſet in the <hi>front,</hi> or firſt place of all; as in the 32, in the 112, in the 119, and in the 128. Again, in this the Pſalmiſt ends with <hi>our</hi> bleſſedneſſe, and begins with <hi>God's;</hi> BLESSED BE THE LORD MY STRENGTH. In the 41 Pſalme, contrary, he makes his <hi>exordium</hi> from <hi>mans;</hi> BLESSED IS HE THAT CONSIDERETH THE POORE: his <hi>concluſion</hi> with <hi>God's;</hi> BLES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SED BE THE LORD GOD OF ISRAEL. I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obſerve theſe variations, becauſe they are helpfull to the underſtanding both of the <hi>eſſence,</hi> and <hi>ſplendour</hi> of true happineſſe. To the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>eſſence</hi> they help, becauſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate how our own happineſſe is enfolded in the glory of God, and ſubordinate unto it. As we cannot begin with <hi>Beatus,</hi> unleſſe we end with <hi>Benedictus:</hi> ſo we muſt begin with <hi>Benedictus,</hi> that we may end with <hi>Beatus.</hi> The reaſon is this, Becauſe the glory of God it is as well the <hi>conſummation,</hi> as the <hi>introduction</hi> to a Chriſtians happineſſe. Therefore as in the other Pſalme he begins below, and ends upwards: ſo in this, having
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156852:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:156852:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:156852:7"/>begun from above with that which is principall, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord;</hi> he fixeth his ſecond thoughts upon the ſubordinate, <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> or <hi>happy are the people.</hi> He could not proceed in a better order: he firſt looks up to <hi>Gods</hi> kingdome, then reflects upon his <hi>own;</hi> as not meaning to <hi>take</hi> bleſſedneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had <hi>given it.</hi> There is no man can think, but this is the beſt method. It is the method of Saints, as we ſee 1. Sam. 25.32, 33. and 2. Chron. 31.8. Firſt, <hi>Bleſſed be the God of Iſrael;</hi> then, <hi>Bleſſed be the people of Iſrael.</hi> Nay, it is the method of Angels:
<note place="margin">Luke 2.14.</note> they firſt ſing, <hi>Glorie to God;</hi> then, <hi>Good will towards men.</hi> It muſt alſo be the method of every Chriſtian, whenſoever we are about the wiſhing of bleſſedneſſe, either to our-ſelves or others, to begin from heaven, and aſcribe it firſt to the LORD. That we may <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi> we muſt <hi>give:</hi> give what we <hi>have,</hi> and give what we <hi>mean to have.</hi> To <hi>give</hi> is the way to <hi>get:</hi> both to get the <hi>thing,</hi> and to get the <hi>greater degree.</hi> It is an undeniable conſequence, If beatitude be the ultimate end of man, and the glorie of God the ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate end of our very beatification; then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes neceſſarily, That by giving more glorie to God we gain more of beatitude to our ſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe more of the ſupreme and beatificall end. So that he who will attain to the Pſalmiſt's <hi>comfort,</hi> muſt obſerve alſo the Pſalmiſt's <hi>order:</hi> that he may <hi>end</hi> aſſuredly with BEATUS, he muſt learn to <hi>begin</hi> with BENEDICTUS. That's the firſt conſiderable thing in the order as touching the <hi>eſſence</hi> of true happineſſe. The other is concerning the <hi>ſplendour,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:156852:7"/>which flowes from the other part of the variation: in that the Pſalmiſt doth end this pſalme, as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins divers of the reſt, with <hi>Happy</hi> or <hi>Bleſſed;</hi> to repreſent, as it were, unto us <hi>utramque ſplendor is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginam,</hi> the two great excellencies of bleſſedneſſe by the double ſituation of it. Happineſſe is both the <hi>bonum Primum,</hi> and the <hi>bonum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimum,</hi> of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: the <hi>ſpring</hi> of all good things, and the <hi>crown:</hi> the <hi>ſpire,</hi> and the <hi>baſis:</hi> the <hi>first</hi> and the <hi>laſt</hi> of things to be deſired; the firſt for <hi>eminence,</hi> the laſt for <hi>fruition.</hi> In the <hi>deſcents</hi> of Chriſtianitie the firſt, becauſe we move from it to inferiour ends: happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe giveth law to all our actions; we move from it, that we may in time come to the poſſeſſion of it. In the order of <hi>aſcent</hi> it is the laſt: for having climb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed once thither, we go no further, but ſet up our reſt. It hath this reſemblance with God himſelf, who is the Doner of it, That it is both the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and the end, before which nothing ſhould be loved, and after which nothing can be deſired. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to theſe two reſpects are the poſitures of happineſſe in the Pſalmes. As in military affairs, it is the cuſtome of Emperours to promiſe the Donative to their ſouldiers when they go forth to warre, that they may encourage them; but not to give it till the warre be ended, that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them for their ſervice: In like manner (ſaith S. Ambroſe) doth the Pſalmiſt: <hi>velut praeco magni Imperatoris,</hi> he diſpoſeth of beatitude both wayes: he prefixeth it to the beginning of ſome Pſalmes, that thereby we might be invited to pietie; he annexeth it to the end of others, to teach us not to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156852:8"/>look for it before our work be done. So even by this we may learn how to order and diſpoſe of our ſelves to happineſſe. Since it hath the <hi>double refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> it muſt have alſo the <hi>double honour,</hi> and the <hi>double esteem,</hi> yea and our <hi>double endeavours</hi> for the attaining of it. Then we give it the <hi>double,</hi> when we ſet it in <hi>both</hi> places, make it both our <hi>firſt</hi> and our <hi>last,</hi> the <hi>prime</hi> of our life, and the <hi>perſeverance.</hi> We muſt look through all things upon happineſſe, and through happineſſe upon all: through all upon it, as not reſting in any thing elſe; and through it upon all, as ſeaſoning every act of our life with the thought of happineſſe. Otherwiſe, if we think to give it our laſt reſpects without our firſt, pretend what we will, there is no hope to overtake it. Thus farre even worldly men will go: they are willing enough to heare that they muſt make it their laſt work, and they fulfill it in a ſort to the <hi>let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> but not to the <hi>meaning.</hi> The love, the hope, the care of their own happineſſe, they put them off all to the laſt: A very prepoſterous courſe for a man to begin where and when he ſhould have end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to defer his firſt of motion to his laſt of reſt. It is too late for the fooliſh Virgins to cry,
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>Lord open</hi> when the doore is ſhut: and a vain thing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect happineſſe as our end, unleſſe we make it our beginning, and give it the ſame place in our hearts and actions, which holy David affords it in his meditations: the firſt place in other Pſalmes, as the beſt introduction to all other diſcourſes; the laſt in this, as a delightfull farwell to be alwayes freſh in remembrance. That ſhall ſerve for the firſt ſtep of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156852:8"/>the Gradation, the <hi>generall</hi> part of the argument handled: It is <hi>De</hi> FELICITATE.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is more <hi>ſpeciall:</hi> it is <hi>de felicitate Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li;</hi> HAPPY, or, BLESSED ARE THE PEOPLE. In the former part of the Pſalme he ſpeaks of ſuch things as concern his <hi>own</hi> happineſſe; <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord</hi> MY <hi>ſtrength,</hi> verſ. 1. <hi>Send down from above, and ſave</hi> ME <hi>out of the great waters,</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>Rid</hi> ME <hi>and deliver</hi> ME <hi>from the hand of ſtrange children,</hi> verſ. 11. And he might as eaſily have continued the ſame ſtrain in the clauſes following, <hi>That</hi> MY <hi>ſonnes may grow up as the young plants,</hi> MY <hi>daughters may be as the poliſhed corners of the temple,</hi> MY <hi>ſheep fruitfull,</hi> MY <hi>oxen ſtrong,</hi> MY <hi>garners full and plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:</hi> and accordingly he might have concluded it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>Happy ſhall</hi> I <hi>be, if I be in ſuch a caſe.</hi> This, I ſay, he might have done, nay, this he would have done, if his deſires had reflected onely upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But being of a diffuſive heart, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what belonged to the neighbourhoods of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as loth to enjoy this happineſſe alone, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters his ſtyle, and (being in the height of well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhes to himſelf) he turns the ſingular into a plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, <hi>Our ſheep, Our oxen, Our garners, Our ſonnes and daughters;</hi> that he might compendiate all in this, <hi>Happy are the people.</hi> Here's a true teſtimonie both of a religious and generous mind, who knew in his moſt retired thoughts to look out of himſelf, and to be mindfull of the publick welfare in his privateſt meditations. S. Ambroſe obſerves it as a clear cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a noble ſpirit, to do what tends to the publick good, though to his own diſadvantage:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156852:9"/>And Salvian, in his firſt <hi>De providentia,</hi> doth rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon this as the principall thing which made the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bii and the Fabricii, and other Romane Worthies ſo renowned in their times, That they were content to expoſe themſelves to want and danger for the proſperitie and ſafetie of the publick. But (alas!) there are few ſuch ſpirits in our time: It is a rare thing to find a private man, who cordially devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelf to the good of the Communitie. It was the complaint of Plato in his time, That every man was impetuouſly carried <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and of Thucydides the Hiſtorian in his, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nuſquiſque rem ſuam urget:</hi> and of Tacitus in his, <hi>Privata cuique ſtimulatio, &amp; vile decus publicum.</hi> S. Paul himſelf was driven to this complaint, Phil. 2.21. <hi>All ſeek their own.</hi> Where he left we may take it up: Our <hi>own</hi> ſettling, our <hi>own</hi> ſecuritie, our <hi>own</hi> wealth, our <hi>own</hi> advancement, is all we generally look after. There is hardly any man to be found, whoſe bent is not towards himſelf: Whereas the publick is the private infinitely multiplied; and ſo much the more of nearer concernment, as it is of larger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion: whereas again man is onely a world in a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurative ſenſe of ſpeaking, and that but a micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme or little world, that is in effect, a ſmall part of the great; yet, as in ſome other things, ſo in this alſo it falls out, The <hi>Allegorie</hi> devoures the <hi>letter,</hi> the <hi>private</hi> eats up the <hi>publick,</hi> the <hi>part</hi> the <hi>whole,</hi> the overweaning reſpect to the <hi>little world</hi> doth every where almoſt overturn the <hi>greater.</hi> I know there are many which make fair ſhews, goodly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, great oſtentation of the contrary: You ſhall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156852:9"/>have them often crying out, <hi>The Publick, the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick;</hi> and as faſt as the Jews did, <hi>The Temple, the Temple:</hi> but it is with the like inſyncetitie; for their aim is wholly for themſelves. So we ſhew our ſelves hypocrites even in things civill, as well as in religion. Each godly man is of another tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. His word is that of S. Ambroſe, <hi>Mihi parci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, for is totus:</hi> or that of the Oratour in Saluſt, <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum en Caius Cotta, voveo, dedóque me pro Republica.</hi> It was a brave reſolution in a Heathen: but it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns us Chriſtians more. For he was onely a part of one Communitie: we, each of us have a ſhare in two; being members of the Church, as well as the State. So there is a double tie upon us: and that we ſhould daily remember it, it is inſinuated in the Lord's prayer: in which as there is one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe petition for the publick; ſo there is a reſpect had to it in all. There is nothing ſingular, not an <hi>I,</hi> nor a <hi>Me,</hi> nor a <hi>Mine;</hi> but all plurall, <hi>We, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, Our:</hi> noting that it is every mans duty, even in his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to be zealous for the Communitie. But the text will not allow me that ſcope, to ſpeak of this zeal to the publick as 'tis the <hi>dutie</hi> of private men, but as it is an <hi>excellencie</hi> of Kings and Princes. It's true, I might call it a <hi>duty</hi> even in them alſo; God requires it of them as a <hi>dutie:</hi> but it becomes us to repute it an <hi>excellencie,</hi> both becauſe the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit is ours which redounds from thence, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe becauſe it is more eminent and illuſtrious in them, then in other men. In others it's <hi>limited</hi> and <hi>miniſteriall,</hi> in a Prince <hi>ſupreme</hi> and <hi>univerſall.</hi> He is the influxive head, who both governs the whole
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156852:10"/>bodie, and every member which is any way ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the bodie: The glorious Sunne that gives light both to the world, and to the ſtarres themſelves, which in their ſeverall ſtations are uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the world. Here's enough to define it an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie,</hi> to have the care and truſt of the whole in himſelf. Yea but further, to tender it as himſelf, and to ſet the weal of the publick in equipage with his own happineſſe, and to fold them up together, his own in the publick and the publick in his own; is ſo high an aſcent of goodneſſe, that it were a great wrong to ſuch vertue, to ſtyle it by any leſſe name then an <hi>excellencie.</hi> In this particular I might eaſily be large: but it requires not ſo much proofs, as acknowledgements and retributions. Therefore I will briefly proceed both wayes: and firſt give you a few examples for proofs; and then, I am ſure, there is no man ſo unworthy, but will think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf obliged to retributions. The firſt example ſhall be taken from Moſes: whom Philo reckons among Kings; and ſo doth the Scripture, Deut. 33.5. For howſoever he had not the <hi>name,</hi> he had the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authority:</hi> yet even in that power he was not more Regal, then in his tenderneſſe over the people. At one time his tenderneſſe was ſo great toward them, that becauſe he could not do them ſo much good as he deſired, he beſought the Lord to take away his life; Numb. 11.15. At another time he was ſo perplexed with the fear of their deſtruction, that he requeſted of God, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to keep them ſtill in the land of the living, or to blot him out of the book of life; Exod. 32.32.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156852:10"/>hereby ſhewing himſelf not onely <hi>the miracle of Nature,</hi> as Philo calls him, but of Grace too, in pledging for them that which was more worth then his life, his very ſalvation. It was a rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Caſtor and Pollux, ſo highly magnified by Authours, That being twinnes, and (as the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets feigned) one born mortall, the other immortall, Pollux (to ſhew his love to his brother) yielded ſo farre, as to take to himſelf a part of his brothers mortalitie, and to lend him as much of his own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie: being better pleaſed to enjoy a half im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie with the good of his brother, then a whole one alone by himſelf. It is known by all to be a fiction: yet if it were true, it is farre ſhort of this proffer of Moſes. He knew full well what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to immortalitie, and to the favour of God: yet in effect he beſeecheth God, either to take them into his favour, or to put him out of it; as content to hazard not half his immortalitie, but all, out of his love to the Iſraelites, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they were a people ungratefull both towards him and towards God. After this of Moſes I know no example ſo tranſcending as that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet David: who (beſides that he urgeth it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in every Pſalme, <hi>The peace of Jeruſalem, The ſalvation of Iſrael, The felicitie of Gods choſen, The bleſsing of the people</hi>) in one place he argues for it even to his own deſtruction: You have it 1. Chron. 21.16, 17. It is there recorded, that ſeeing the angel of the Lord with his ſword drawn over Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem to deſtroy it, he thus reaſons with God for the ſafeguard of the publick: <hi>Me, me; adſum qui
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156852:11"/>feci;</hi> IT IS I, EVEN I IT IS THAT HAVE SINNED: <hi>In me convertito ferrum;</hi> LET THY HAND BE AGAINST ME, AND AGAINST MY FATHERS HOUSE, NOT ON THY PEOPLE: FOR THESE SHEEP VVHAT HAVE THEY DONE? He that conſiders theſe words will hardly be able to tell what moſt to wonder at; the condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his love, or the overflowing. <hi>He declared here,</hi> ſaith S. Chryſoſtome, <hi>a depth of love</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an affection more ſpatious for <hi>love,</hi> then the ſea for <hi>water;</hi> and, for tenderneſſe, ſofter not onely then <hi>water,</hi> but then <hi>oyl.</hi> To lay down, as it were, his own royall neck under the ſword of the Angel, when he ſaw it hanging over him by a leſſe threed, then that of Damocles: To open his own religious breaſt, to receive the blow, that he might ward it from the people: To value the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſafetie ſo farre above his own, as to interpoſe himſelf betwixt the ſword and the ſlaughter: O how farre doth he here renounce himſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede, not onely from royaltie, but from life it ſelf! It is much which is mentioned in the text, that he ſhould name the people firſt to the happineſſe: more that he ſhould offer himſelf firſt to the puniſhment: very much, that he ſhould put the people betwixt himſelf and the bleſſing: farre more, that he ſhould place himſelf betwixt the people and the curſe. He made himſelf in this SPECULUM PRINCIPUM, <hi>the mirrour of Princes:</hi> a mirrour, into which (as we may well preſume) our Gracious Sovereigne King CHARLES hath made frequent and uſefull inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for it is manifeſt by many paſſages of his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156852:11"/>reigne and happy government, that the tenderneſſe of his love towards his people, if it doth not fully reach, yet it comes cloſe up to the receſſions of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid. It is the more remarkable, for that he hath this vertue as it were in proper and by himſelf, he is almoſt the ſole poſſeſſour of it. The moſt of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary men, as living more by <hi>will</hi> then <hi>reaſon,</hi> are all for holding: ſo ſtiffe and inflexible, ſo tenaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and unyielding, even in matters of ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that they will not ſtirre a hair-breadth. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them, perſwade them, convince them; ſtill they keep to this principle (and 'tis none of the beſt) Obtain <hi>all,</hi> Yield <hi>nothing.</hi> It is a Nobler ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that reſides in the breaſt of our Sovereigne, as appeares by his manifold yieldings and receſſions. Of ſuch receſſions we have many inſtances in the courſe of his Majeſties government. I might go as farre back as his firſt coming to the Crown: when he receded from his own profit, in taking upon him the payment of his Fathers debts, which were great, and but ſmall ſupplies to be expected from an empty Exchequer: yet the love of juſtice and his peoples emolument overſwayed him, and armed him with Epaminondas his reſolution, <hi>Totius Orbis divitias deſpicere, prae patriae charitate.</hi> Having but glanced at that, I might draw a little nearer, to the third of his reigne: when, in that Parliament of <hi>Tertio,</hi> he was pleaſed to ſigne the, ſo much deſired, Petition of Right a Title which, I confeſſe, takes me much: both becauſe it ſpeaks the dutifulneſſe of the ſubject, in petitioning, although for right; and the great goodneſſe of a Gracious Prince,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156852:12"/>who knows how to recede from power, and in ſome caſe even from prerogative, when beſought by prayers; and rejoyceth, not to <hi>ſell</hi> his favours, but to <hi>give</hi> them. For I have heard ſome wiſe men ſay, That that ſingle grant was equivalent to twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſubſidies. But the time will not give me leave to dwell, as I ſhould, upon particulars: therefore I will call you nearer to the tranſient remembrance (and but the tranſient, for it is no pleaſure to revive it) of the commotions in the North. The eyes of the whole world were upon that action, and they all are witneſſes what pains and travell were taken, what clemencie and indulgence was uſed, what yieldings and condeſcentions, both in point of honour and power, to purchaſe, as it were, by a price paid out of himſelf, the peace and tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of both kingdomes. Whereby he made all men underſtand, how much more pleaſing it was to his Princely diſpoſition, with Cyrus in Xenophon, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and to conquer, not by <hi>might,</hi> but by <hi>clemencie.</hi> By <hi>clemencie,</hi> I ſay, the word which I named before, and I cannot name it too often. It is the vertue God moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in, to exerciſe himſelf; and 'tis the copie alſo which he ſets us to write after: It is the vertue which draws both eyes and hearts unto it; in that it maketh Royaltie it ſelf, which is ſo farre above, to become beneficiall and ſovereigne: It corrects the brightneſſe of Majeſtie, calmes the ſtrictneſſe of Juſtice, lightens the weight of Power, attempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates whatſoever might cauſe terrour to our mind and liking. If we never had known it before, yet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156852:12"/>the onely time of this Parliament would teach us ſufficiently how much we ow to the King's cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie. The laws and ſtatutes which have been made this laſt yeare, are laſting and ſpeaking mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of theſe Royall receſſions, as well to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, as to our ſelves. Surely if the true picture and reſemblance of a Prince be in his laws; it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied, that in the Acts, for trienniall Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments, for the continuation of the Parliament now being, for the regulating of impoſitions, preſſing of ſouldiers, courts of Judicature, and others not a few of the like nature, are the lineaments, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions to the life, of the prefect portraiture of a Benigne and Gracious Prince, who ſeems reſolved of a new way, and hitherto unheard of, by whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome laws to <hi>enlarge his ſubjects,</hi> and to <hi>confine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> Yet it may be ſaid, It is not his onely hand which is in theſe laws: the <hi>propoſall</hi> of them is from others, although the <hi>ratification</hi> be in him. Be it ſo: But the ratification is ten fold to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall; nay, it is the life and eſſence of a law. So we ow the laws themſelves to his goodneſſe. Nay, and if it be granted, that the propoſall of ſuch laws comes from others, let us then look to the many gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious meſſages, which occaſionally have been ſent, at ſeverall times, to that great Aſſemblie. In theſe he ſpeaks onely by himſelf; and in ſo gracious a manner, that to reade ſome paſſages, would <hi>raviſh</hi> a loyall heart, as well as <hi>endear</hi> it. In ſome of them we may ſee, how he puts the happineſſe of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into the ſame proximitie with his own: in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, how he neglects his own for our accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156852:13"/>In that of January the 20, you have theſe golden words: That he will rather lay by any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reſpect of his Own dignitie, then loſe time for the Publick good: That, out of his Fatherly care of his people, he will be ready, both to equall, and to exceed the greateſt examples of the moſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Princes, in their Acts of Grace and Favour to their people. Again, in that of the 28 of Janua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry there is yet more tenderneſſe. He calles God to witneſſe (and with him the atteſtation of that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Name is very religious) that the preſervation of the publick peace, the law and the libertie of the ſubject, is and ſhall alwayes be as much his care and induſtrie, as the ſafety of his own life, or the lives of his deareſt children. Laſtly, in the other of the 15 of March there is more then yieldings and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions; a gracious prevention of our deſires: for he is pleaſed to excite and call upon that Great Councell, even the ſecond time, to prepare with all ſpeed ſuch Acts, as ſhall be for the eſtabliſhment of their priviledges, the free and quiet enjoying their eſtates and fortunes, the liberties of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the ſecuritie of the true Religion now profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Church of England. What now ſhall we ſay to theſe things? Is not that of Solomon made good unto us (Prov. 16.10.) <hi>A Divine ſentence is in the lips of the King?</hi> Have we not good cauſe to take up Ezra's benediction (Ezr. 7.27.) <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord which hath put ſuch things as theſe into the Kings heart?</hi> Such things as theſe we were not ſo ambitious as to hope for: I truſt we ſhall not be ſo unworthy as to forget. For my ſelf, I could wiſh that, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156852:13"/>to the dutie of this day, I could ſet them forth as they deſerve. But they need no varniſh of Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie: neither was it my intendment to uſe them fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then for the proof of the propoſition in hand; to ſhew you how this higheſt excellencie of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in the care of their peoples happineſſe, is radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant in our Gracious Sovereigne. Yet you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member alſo that I told you, The point needs not ſo much <hi>proofs,</hi> as <hi>retributions.</hi> It calls aloud upon us for all dutifull returns, of honour, love, obedience, loyaltie, and thankfull acknowledgements, into that Royall boſome, the firſt mover and originall under God of our happineſſe. In the ſphere of Nature there is none of us ignorant, how willing the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are to make return to the head, for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and influence they receive from thence: they will undergo hardſhip, expoſe themſelves to danger, recede from things convenient, nay neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; they will not grudge at any plentie or honour which is beſtowed upon the head; knowing by inſtinct that from the head the benefit of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounds to them. It is likewiſe obvious in the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of families, which are as States epitomized, that both honour and dutie belong to the <hi>Paterfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliâs,</hi> not onely for the right he hath in the houſe, but for the proviſion and ſupport and comfort which all receive from him. Now Kings, by way of excellencie, are Fathers, who look upon all their ſubjects as ſo many children, and (with that Noble Emperour) account equally as daughters <hi>Rempubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam &amp; Juliam.</hi> The very Heathen, which ſaw onely the outſide or Civill part, reputed them as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156852:14"/>Fathers: but the Prophet Iſaiah, when he ſpeaks of the Church, goes further, and calls them <hi>Nurſing Fathers:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 49.23.</note> a word which in propriety of ſpeech might ſeem incongruous; becauſe they have no more of the nurſe, then the boſome; nothing at all of the breaſts, if what is wanting in the ſex were not ſupplied by their tenderneſſe. Benignitie, and clemencie, and ſweetneſſe of diſpoſition, and faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of acceſſe, and compaſſion toward the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, theſe are their breaſts, more breaſts then two; the ſame both their <hi>breasts</hi> and their <hi>bowels,</hi> which day by day they open to thouſands <hi>ſeverally,</hi> and to all at <hi>once,</hi> for the ſuckling and foſtering of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. Therefore it behoves us to think of <hi>returns.</hi> By this word Chriſt read us the leſſon, Matth. 22.21. <hi>Bender,</hi> or <hi>Return unto Ceſar the things which are Ceſars,</hi> or <hi>the things which are from Ceſar.</hi> The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of lives, and fortunes, and worldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts; let him have theſe back again in the honour, love, fear, obedience, ſupplies which belong to the Sovereigne <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Parent</hi> of a beloved people: that his throne may be eſtabliſhed by your loyalty, his reigne ſtill proſperous by your prayers &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, his life lengthened by yeares taken forth of your own: that ſo he may long rejoyce to ſay with David, <hi>Happy are the people.</hi> So I have done with the ſecond ſtep of the Gradation, the <hi>ſpeciall</hi> part of the argument here handled; It is <hi>De felicitate Populi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third is yet <hi>more ſpeciall:</hi> It is not onely <hi>De felicitate Populi,</hi> but <hi>De felicitate Populari,</hi> that is, <hi>De Hac felicitate populi,</hi> or <hi>De hoc Genere felicitatis:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156852:14"/>Beatus cui SIC, Happy they who are in</hi> SUCH A CASE, or CONDITION. What that condition is, you may ſee in the former words; in which there are ſeverall bleſſings mentioned, and all of them temporall. Plenty is one, in thoſe words, <hi>That our garners may be filled with all manner of ſtore; our oxen ſtrong to labour; our ſheep bring forth thouſands.</hi> Peace is another, in theſe words, <hi>That there be no leading in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to captivitie, no complaining in our ſtreets.</hi> Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people, eſpecially ſuch as are vertuous, a third, in thoſe, <hi>That our ſonnes may grow up as the young plants, our daughters may be as the poliſhed cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the temple.</hi> The ſafetie and proſperitie of David their King, a fourth (or rather a firſt, for it is firſt mentioned) <hi>He giveth ſalvation,</hi> or <hi>victorie to Kings, and delivereth David his ſervant from the peril of the ſword.</hi> Of all theſe civill threeds the Pſalmiſt twiſts this wreath of Happineſſe; <hi>Happy they who are in ſuch a caſe.</hi> Now hence ariſeth the ſcruple: Why David, a man of ſo heavenly a temper, and of ſo good a judgment in things which concern ſalvation; that he is ſaid to be <hi>A man after Gods own heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 13.14.</note> ſhould place felicitie in theſe temporalls. Devout S. Paul, who of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers came neareſt to Davids ſpirit, had theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things in no better eſteem, then as <hi>droſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> or <hi>dung:</hi> and our bleſſed Saviour, in his firſt Sermon, thought good to begin the chain of happineſſe from povertie, and to ſecond it from hunger,
<note place="margin">Matt. 5.</note> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue it from ſuffering perſecution. <hi>Non dixit,</hi> BEATI DIVITES, <hi>ſed,</hi> BEATI PAUPERES, as S. Ambroſe obſerveth. In this, I ſay, is the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156852:15"/>ſcruple, That Chriſt ſhould begin bleſſedneſſe from <hi>povertie,</hi> and David place it in <hi>abundance:</hi> that things earthly ſhould be as <hi>droſſe</hi> to Paul, and as <hi>happineſſe</hi> to David. This ſcruple wrought ſo farre with ſome Interpreters, that they conceived it to be a defective or imperfect ſentence, and that the Pſalmiſt uttered it in the perſon of a worldly man: like that of Solomon, Eccl. 2.24. <hi>There is nothing better for a man, then to cat and drink, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore, to take off the ſuſpicion of a paradox, they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Dixerunt:</hi> BEATUM <hi>[dixerunt]</hi> POPU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LUM CUI HAEC SUNT, <hi>Men uſually ſay,</hi> HAPPY ARE THE PEOPLE IN SUCH A CASE. But we need not flee to this refuge: It is neither a <hi>defective</hi> nor a <hi>paradox;</hi> but a <hi>full</hi> and <hi>true</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, agreeable both to the tenour of other Scriptures, and alſo to the analogie of faith. For firſt, the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks not here, as in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of the happineſſe of a <hi>man,</hi> but of the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a <hi>people:</hi> it is not <hi>Beatus homo,</hi> but; <hi>Beatus populus.</hi> In ſome other places, where he treats of the happineſſe of a man, he circumſcribes it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with things ſpirituall:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>a</hi> Pſal. 32.2.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom the LORD imputeth no ſinne, and in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>b</hi> Pſal. 112.1.</note> Bleſsed is the man that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the LORD:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>c</hi> Pſal. 40.4.</note> Bleſſed is that man that maketh the Lord his truſt:</hi> and the
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>d</hi> Pſal 65.4. &amp; 84.5. &amp; 128.1.</note> like. Here otherwiſe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he ſpeaks of the happineſſe of a people, he might uſe more libertie to take in theſe outward ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments, as having a nearer relation to the happineſſe of a <hi>Nation</hi> or <hi>Kingdome,</hi> then abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively of a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> Howſoever Ariſtotle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156852:15"/>in the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of his Politicks, that there is the ſame happineſſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>of a ſingle man and of a whole citie:</hi> Yet there is a great deal of difference, which he, being not inſtructed in Chriſtianity, could not obſerve. Look as on the one ſide, the being of a State or Nation, as a collective bodie, is not ſo ordered to immortalitie, nor by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to happineſſe, as the being of a man: ſo on the other, the concurrence of temporall good things is in no wiſe ſo eſſentiall or requiſite to the happineſſe of a man, as to the being and well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo to the happineſſe of a State or people. Experience tells us that a man may be happy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>children;</hi> a State cannot be ſo without <hi>people:</hi> a private man may keep his hold of happineſſe, though <hi>poore</hi> and <hi>afflicted</hi> in the world; a State is onely then happy, when 'tis <hi>flouriſhing</hi> and <hi>proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,</hi> abounding with peace, plentie, people, and other civill acceſſions. Men are the walls for ſtrength, women the nurſeries for encreaſe, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren the pledges of perpetuity, money as the vitall breath, peace as the naturall heat, plentie as the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall moiſture, religious and juſt government as the form or ſoul of a bodie politick. Upon this ground the Pſalmiſt well knowing how conducing theſe outward things are to popular happineſſe, he caſts them all into the definition; his preſent ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument being the happineſſe of a people. In the ſecond place, admit he had ſpake here of the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of a man, or a Chriſtian: yet he mentions not theſe temporalls, either as the <hi>all,</hi> or the <hi>onely,</hi> or the <hi>chief</hi> of happineſſe; but as the <hi>concomitants</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:156852:16"/>and <hi>acceſſories.</hi> They have not an <hi>eſſentiall</hi> influx or ingredience into it: but a <hi>ſecondarie</hi> and <hi>accidentall</hi> reſpect they have in theſe two conſiderations. Firſt they are <hi>ornamenta,</hi> as <hi>garniſhings,</hi> which give a gloſſe and luſtre to vertue, and make it more ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did. The Moraliſts ſay well, that they are as ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows to a picture, or garments to a comely perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. Now as in theſe, the ſhadowing makes not the colour of a picture truly better, but onely ſeem better, and appear more freſh and orient; and as garments do indeed adorn the bodie now in the ſtate of corruption; whereas, if man had ſtood in his integritie, they had been uſeleſſe for ornament, as well as for neceſſitie: So likewiſe theſe outward things, although in themſelves they have nothing of true happineſſe, yet becauſe they render it more beauteous and gracefull, as the ſtate of vertue now ſtands in reſpect of our converſe with men, we may well reckon them without prejudice to vertue <hi>inter or namenta.</hi> Then ſecondly, they are <hi>adminicula</hi> alſo, <hi>helps</hi> and <hi>adjuments,</hi> as <hi>hand-maids</hi> to pietie, without which vertue is impotent. Were a man all ſoul, vertue alone were ſufficient; it is enough by it ſelf for the happineſſe of the mind: but being partly bodie, and enjoying corporall ſocietie with others, he ſtands in need of things corporall, to keep vertue in exerciſe. Want clippes the wings of vertue, that a man cannot feed the hungry, or cloth the naked, or enlarge himſelf to the good of others: on the other ſide, this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers term it, ſets vertue at libertie, and gives it ſcope to be operative. As fire, the more aire &amp; few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:156852:16"/>you give it, the more it diffuſeth it ſelf: ſo the more health, peace, plentie, friends, or authoritie we have; the more power, freedome and advantage we have to do vertuouſly. Put now all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; the reaſon is evident, why the Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid here placeth this happineſſe in the things which are worſe; becauſe they are ſerviceable to the things which are better. Howſoever he reſerves the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the better till afterward; Yet he would give us to underſtand, that even theſe inferiour things are the good bleſſings of God, and ſuch bleſſings, as being put together, make up one part of the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a people. It is true of popular happineſſe, as well as perſonall, It is not one ſingle good, but the aggregation or affluence of many. In the twenty eighth of Deuteronomie, where Moſes deſcribes the bleſſedneſſe promiſed to the Iſraelites, he reckons up all ſorts of outward bleſſings: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to thoſe is the conflux of theſe in this Pſalme: The bleſſing of the <hi>houſe,</hi> and of the <hi>citie; That there be no leading into captivitie, and no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining in the ſtreets:</hi> The bleſſings of the <hi>basket,</hi> and of the <hi>ſtore; That the garners may be filled with plentie:</hi> The bleſſings of the <hi>fruit of the bodie; That the children may be as young plants:</hi> The bleſſings of the <hi>field, That the ſheep may bring forth thouſands, and the oxen be ſtrong to labour:</hi> The bleſſings of <hi>going out</hi> and <hi>coming in; That they may be delivered from the hand of ſtrange children, and ſaved out of great waters.</hi> Here is briefly the compound of the many ſimples which make up this caſe or condition of a peoples happineſſe. And ſurely if by theſe particulars it be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:156852:17"/>defined, we may boldly ſay, The condition is our own, and men may pronounce of us, as truly as of any Nation, that we have been for a long time a <hi>happy people.</hi> Our deliverances from ſtrange chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren have been great and miraculous, and our land it hath been a Goſhen, a <hi>light-ſome land;</hi> whereas the <hi>darkneſſe of diſcomfort</hi> hath reſted upon other Nations. The bleſſings of the citie and field, of the basket and of the ſtore have grown upon us in ſuch abundance, that many men have ſurfetted of plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Our land hath been as an Eden and garden of the Lord for <hi>fruitfulneſſe,</hi> as a Salem for <hi>peace;</hi> whereas other kingdomes do yet grone under the preſſures of <hi>ſword</hi> and <hi>famine.</hi> Beſides theſe, if there be any bleſſing which the Scripture mentions in other places, <hi>Peace in the walls, Plentie in the palaces, Traffick in the ports,</hi> or <hi>Salvation in the gates;</hi> if any part of happineſſe which it ſpeaks of in this Pſalme, for plantings, or buildings, or reapings, or ſtorings, or peoplings; we have had them all in as much fulneſſe as any part of the world, and in more then moſt: onely there is one particular may be queſtioned, or rather cannot be denied, That amidſt the very throng of all theſe bleſſings there are ſome <hi>murmurings and complainings in our ſtreets.</hi> But it need not ſeem ſtrange to us, becauſe it is not new in the world. In the ſtories of all ages we meet with it, That men uſed to complain of their times to be evil, when indeed themſelves made them ſo. I may be bold to ſay, There was cauſe in reſpect of ſinne then, as well as now, eſpecially with godly men, who are ſo good themſelves, that it is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156852:17"/>if they thought times <hi>a little evil</hi> to be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely bad:</hi> as alwayes ſinne ſwells to the eye of grace. But if we ſpeak of outward preſſures and calamities, I am certain there is not cauſe now as then: for the riches of the Kingdome were never ſo great, the peace of the Kingdome never ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, the ſtate of it for all things never ſo proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. Onely we muſt give leave to the world to be like it ſelf: As long as ambition or covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are in the world, men of ſuch ſpirits will cry out, The times are bad, even when they are beſt; becauſe they (in their own bad ſenſe) ſtill deſire to be better. As nothing is enough, ſo nothing is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to a reſtleſſe mind. An inſatiable appetite is alwayes impatient; and, becauſe impatient, queru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. Yet this is not the ſole reaſon: for beſides this humour of appetite, the very corruption of our nature leads us hereunto, To be weary of the preſent. It is the joynt obſervation both of Divines and Moraliſts (as of Salvian, Quintilian, Tacitus, and others, who agree as near almoſt in words as in opinion) <hi>Quòduſitatum eſt ment is humanae vitium, illa magìs ſemper velle quae deſunt; &amp;, veter a quidem in laude, praeſentia in faſtidio ponere.</hi> Our own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience will tell us as much, if we will take pains to obſerve it, How, through the pravity of our own diſpoſitions, whatſoever is preſent proves burdenſome, whether it be good or bad. Salvian, in his third <hi>De Gubernatione,</hi> ſets forth this humour to the life: That men of all times were diſpleaſed with all times: <hi>Si astus eſt,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>de ariditate cauſamur; ſi fluvia, de inundatione conquerimur: ſi
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:156852:18"/>infoecundior annus eſt, accuſamus ſterilitatem; ſi foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundior, vilitatem.</hi> So winter and ſummer are both alike diſtaſtfull to impatient men: In ſcarcity things are too dear, in plentie too cheap: povertie pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and abundance nauſeats. If there be a little too much drought, they cry out of a famine; if a ſhowre or two extraordinary, they are afraid of a deluge. You ſhall heare in good times, <hi>Quid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis cum Davide?</hi> and in bad, <hi>Antigonum effodie:</hi> as we reade of the Iſraelites, That even when God himſelf was pleaſed to order their civill affairs, they were not contented; but ſtill repined, as well when they had manna, as when they wanted it. The reaſon is (as the Greek Hiſtorian notes) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But I hope we Chriſtians are of a better temper. It beſeems not us of all others to be ſo injurious to <hi>God,</hi> who hath ſingled us out to be a happy people: It beſeems us not to be ſo unthankfull to our <hi>Sovereigne,</hi> under whom we enjoy theſe bleſſings. Howſoever it ought to be in the firſt place acknowledged, that the originall of all our happineſſe is from heaven: yet it muſt be confeſt withall, that the cryſtall pipe through which bleſſings are conveyed unto us, is his government: Our peace is from his wiſdome, our plentie from our peace; our proſperitie from our plenty; our ſafetie, our very life, our whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver good of this nature, it is by Gods providence wrapt up in his welfare, whoſe precious life (as the Oratour ſpeaks) is <hi>Vita quaedam publica,</hi> the very <hi>breath of our nostrils</hi> perfumed with multitude of comforts.
<note place="margin">Lam. 4.20.</note> What then remains, but that our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:156852:18"/>ſhould reſult from all, to make our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe complete? that ſo both receiving what we deſire, and retributing what we ow, we may give cauſe unto all Kingdomes to lengthen this acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to ſay, <hi>Happy both Prince and people which are in ſuch a caſe.</hi> So I have done with the firſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall part of the text, the path of <hi>proſperity,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the <hi>civill</hi> reſpect of the day.</p>
            <p>I now proceed to the ſecond, the path of <hi>Pietie,</hi> anſwerable to the <hi>Religious</hi> reſpect; <hi>Yea, happy.</hi> It's the beſt wine to the laſt, though all men be not of this opinion. You ſhall hardly bring a worldly man to think ſo. The world is willing enough to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſter the order of the words, and to give the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritie to Civill happineſſe, as if it were firſt in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitie, becauſe 'tis firſt named: they like it better to heare of the <hi>Cui ſic,</hi> then the <hi>Cui Dominus.</hi> To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent this follie, the Pſalmiſt interpoſeth a caution in this corrective particle, <hi>Yea, Happy.</hi> It hath the force of a revocation, whereby he ſeems to retract what went before, not ſimply and abſolutely, but in a certain degree, leſt worldly men ſhould wreſt it to a miſinterpretation. It is not an <hi>abſolute</hi> revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but a <hi>comparative;</hi> it doth not ſimply deny that there is ſome part of popular happineſſe in theſe outward things, but it preferres the ſpiritualls before them: <hi>Yea,</hi> that is, <hi>Yea more,</hi> or, <hi>Yea rather:</hi> like that of Chriſt in the Goſpel, When one in the companie bleſſed the wombe that bare him, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently replies, <hi>Yea,
<note place="margin">Luk. 11.28.</note> rather bleſſed are they that heare the word of God and keep it.</hi> In like manner the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet David, having firſt premiſed the inferiour part
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:156852:19"/>and outſide of an happy condition; fearing leſt any ſhould of purpoſe miſtake his meaning, and hearing the firſt propoſition, ſhould either there ſet up their reſt, and not at all take in the ſecond; or if take it in, yet do it prepoſterouſly, and give it the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence before the ſecond, according to the worlds order, <hi>Virtus post nummos:</hi> In this reſpect he puts in the clauſe of revocation; whereby he ſhews, that theſe outward things, though <hi>named</hi> firſt, yet they are not to be <hi>reputed</hi> firſt. The particle <hi>Yea</hi> removes them to the ſecond place: it tacitly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the order; and the path of piety, which was <hi>locally</hi> after, it placeth <hi>virtually</hi> before. 'Tis as if he had ſaid, Did I call them <hi>happy,</hi> who are in ſuch a caſe? Nay, <hi>miſerable</hi> are they, if they be onely in ſuch a caſe: The <hi>temporall</hi> part cannot make them ſo without the <hi>ſpirituall.</hi> Admit the windows of the viſible heaven were opened, and all outward bleſſings poured down upon us; admit we did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly enjoy whatſoever the vaſtneſſe of the earth contains in it: tell me, What will it profit to gain all, and to loſe God? If the earth be beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and not heaven; or the materiall heaven be opened, and not the beatificall; or the whole world made ours, and God not ours: we do not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at happineſſe. All that is in the firſt propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is nothing, unleſſe this be added, <hi>Yea, happy are the people which have the</hi> LORD <hi>for their God.</hi> You ſee in this part there is <hi>aliquid quod eminet,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which is tranſcendent: Therefore I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into two particulars; ſee both what it is that tranſcends, and what is the manner of propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:156852:19"/>
            <p>The manner of propounding it, is, as I ſaid, corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, or by way of revocation: the ſumme where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is thus much, That temporalls without ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls, in what abundance ſoever we poſſeſſe them, cannot make us truly happy. They cannot make <hi>happy,</hi> becauſe they cannot make <hi>good.</hi> They may denominate a man to be <hi>rich,</hi> or <hi>great,</hi> or <hi>honourable;</hi> but not to be <hi>vertuous.</hi> Nay, Seneca carrieth it a little further: <hi>Non modò non faciunt bonum, ſed nec divitem;</hi> They are ſo farre from making a man <hi>good,</hi> that they make him not <hi>truly rich;</hi> becauſe they encreaſe deſire, and riches conſiſt in conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Not he that hath little, but he that deſires more is poore: nor he that hath much, but he that wants nothing is rich. Yea, and we may go further then Seneca; They are ſo farre from making <hi>good,</hi> that they often make <hi>evil,</hi> if they be not ſanctified: they poſſeſſe the heart with vile affections, fill it full of carnall and ſinfull deſires. Whereas there are foure good mothers which bring forth ill daughters, proſperitie is one. Truth begets hatred, ſecuritie danger, familiaritie contempt, proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie pride and forgetfulneſſe of God. In this I might well make a ſtop; but there is one degree more: They are ſo farre from <hi>making</hi> good, that they do not <hi>bring</hi> good, but many evils and inconveniences. They bring not the good of <hi>contentment,</hi> but infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite diſtractions: they are <hi>aureae compedes,</hi> as S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard ſpeaks, fetters or manicles which intangle the ſoul, that it cannot attend upon better things: Nor the good of <hi>freedome:</hi> they do enthrall the ſoul to that which is worſe then it ſelf; and it cannot
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:156852:20"/>be apprehended how a thing worſe then our ſelves can make us happy. Laſtly, not the good of <hi>ſafetie:</hi> for they oftentimes expoſe us to dangers. <hi>Multos ſua felicitas ſtravit,</hi> as Gregorie ſpeaks. Many men their lives had been longer, if their riches had been leſſe: their happineſſe made them miſerable; <hi>&amp; conſolationes factae ſunt deſolationes,</hi> as S. Bernard again. Upon theſe grounds the Pſalmiſt had very good reaſon to ſequeſter them from true happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and, by this corrective particle, to reduce them to the ſecond place, though he ſet them in the firſt. He knew very well that they are burdens, ſnares, impediments to pietie, as often as furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances. He knew them to be vain and tranſitory things,
<note place="margin">Prov. 23.5.</note> that we cannot hold. <hi>They make themſelves wings,</hi> as Solomon ſpeaks. They are onely the moveables of happineſſe, <hi>Bractealis felicitas,</hi> as Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as Nazianzene. What's that? S. Auſtin ſeems to tranſlate it, <hi>felicitas fallax,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous and perſonate felicitie: Nay, not onely <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lax,</hi> but <hi>falſa,</hi> fictitious, ſpurious, deceitfull, which leaves the ſoul <hi>empty</hi> when it moſt <hi>fills</hi> it: that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt true which the ſame Father addes, <hi>felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas fallax, major infelicitas; &amp; falſa felicitas, vera miſeria.</hi> Therefore, that I may ſhut up this point, let this be the uſe of it. We muſt learn from hence to regulate our judgements according to the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Spirit revealed in the word: And that we may do, if we keep to Gods method, and ſet every thing in the due place, where God hath ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. Now the Scripture conſtantly doth give the inferiour place to theſe temporall things. If to come
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:156852:20"/>after, be inferiour; it ſets them there: <hi>Seek firſt the kingdome of God,</hi> &amp;c. Matth. 6.33. If to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, be inferiour, it placeth them there: <hi>Set your affection on things above,</hi> &amp;c. Coloſſ. 3.2. Even gold and ſilver, the beſt of theſe things, they are ſeated under the feet of men, and the whole world under the feet of a Chriſtian, Rev. 12.1. to teach us to deſpiſe it. Laſtly, if to be on the left hand, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour; the Scripture reckons them there too: they are called <hi>the bleſsings of the left hand,</hi> to teach us to give them the ſame place in our affections. In one ſenſe, we may put them on the right, by uſing them to God's glorie: but in love and eſteem they muſt be on the left. S. Hierome illuſtrates it by this ſimilitude: As flax when it is on the diſtaffe, it is on the left hand; but when it is ſpunne into yarn, and put on the ſpindle, it is on the right: ſo temporall things in themſelves, when firſt we receive them, they are as flax on the diſtaffe, all this while on the left hand; but ſpinne them forth, and uſe them to God's glorie, they are as yarn on the ſpindle, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the right. Thus we muſt learn to order them: to the right hand onely for <hi>uſe,</hi> to the left for <hi>valuation.</hi> Otherwiſe, if we pervert God's order, and put them on the <hi>right;</hi> it is to be feared they will ſet us on the <hi>left</hi> at the day of judgement: if we elevate them <hi>above,</hi> they will keep us <hi>below;</hi> and make us come <hi>after,</hi> if we ſet them <hi>before.</hi> The higheſt place they can have, is to be ſeconds to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: here holy David placeth them: though he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions pietie laſt, yet he giveth it the precedence in this word of revocation, <hi>Yea, happie;</hi> that is, <hi>Yea
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:156852:21"/>firſt, yea more, yea more truly happie.</hi> That ſhall ſerve for the firſt particular, the manner of propounding this truth unto us.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is the thing it ſelf which tranſcends, in theſe words, <hi>whoſe God is the</hi> LORD, or, <hi>who have the</hi> LORD <hi>for their God.</hi> In the generall it is an <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,</hi> as well as <hi>tranſcendent.</hi> An ordinary, becauſe all partake of this priviledge. Whereupon S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin asks the queſtion, <hi>Cujus non eſt Deus?</hi> But S. Hierome reſolves it; <hi>Naturaâ Deus omnium, volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate paucorum:</hi> In a communitie the God of all, even to the ſparrow on the houſe top, and graſſe of the field; but the God of the righteous after a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar manner. To come to the meaning; we muſt let go the generall, this <hi>ordo communis providentiae,</hi> as he is <hi>Dominus omnium,</hi> the Lord of all creatures: this brings not happineſſe along with it: God's or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and generall providence intitles not to that ſupreme bleſſedneſſe, which is in himſelf. The ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall references are onely intended: and thoſe we may reduce to theſe two heads. The firſt is <hi>ordo ſpecialis influxûs,</hi> on God's part, the reſpect of his being gracious to us. Then the Lord is <hi>our God,</hi> when he ſhews himſelf benigne and propitious, when he manifeſts his mercie and goodneſſe in the wayes of grace and means of ſalvation. It is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded Pſalme 65.4. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whom thou chooſeſt:</hi> and Pſalme 33.12. <hi>Bleſſed is the nation, whoſe God is the</hi> LORD, <hi>and the people whom he hath choſen for his own inheritance.</hi> Being thus taken, it affords us this meditation, That there is no true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, but in the favour of God, and light of his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:156852:21"/>countenance; that is, in God himſelf: both becauſe happineſſe is onely <hi>from him,</hi> he is the onely au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of it: <hi>Non facit beatum hominem, niſi qui ſecit hominem; — Qui dedit ut homines ſimus, ſolus dat ut beati ſimus;</hi> He onely makes <hi>Saints</hi> who makes <hi>men:</hi> 'tis S. Auſtin's elegant expreſſion. Then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as it is onely <hi>from God,</hi> ſo it is onely <hi>in God.</hi> As the ſoul, ſaith Auſtin, is <hi>vita carnis;</hi> ſo God is the <hi>beata vita hominis,</hi> ſo fully, that a man cannot be happy either way, <hi>nec abſque Deo, nec extra De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> not <hi>without God,</hi> becauſe he is the <hi>Doner;</hi> not <hi>out of God,</hi> becauſe he is the <hi>thing it ſelf,</hi> and all which belongs to it. As S. Ambroſe of the foure beatitudes in S. Luke compared with the eight in S. Matthew; <hi>In iſtis octa illae quatuer ſunt, &amp; in iſtis quatuer illae octo:</hi> and as King Porus, when Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander askt him how he would be uſed, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in one word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>like a King.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander again replying, Do you deſire nothing elſe? No, ſaith he: all things are in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. So in this which we are now about it holds much more: both the <hi>foure,</hi> and the <hi>eight,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, they are in God; ſo that he who hath God, muſt needs have all things, becauſe God is all things. There is no notion under which we can couch beatitude, but we may find it in God by way of eminencie: if as a ſtate of joy, or glory, or wealth, or tranquillitie, or ſecuritie; God is all theſe: if as a ſtate of perfection, ſalvation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution; God is all theſe: not onely the <hi>giver of the reward,</hi> but the <hi>reward it ſelf;</hi> both our <hi>bonum,</hi> and our <hi>ſummum.</hi> A Chriſtian is never truly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:156852:22"/>till he can find himſelf and all things in God. The fruition of God, it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>(as Peluſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſpeaks) the very top of the ſpire or pinacle of beatitude both here and in heaven. <hi>In hoc un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit as beatitudinis cliquatur,</hi> to uſe Tertullians words. Were a man in paradiſe, were he in heaven it ſelf, and had not God; he could not be happy. Were he on Job's dunghill, in Daniels den, in the belly of hell with Jonah, nay in the infernall hell with Dives, and yet had God; he could not be miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: for heaven is whereſoever God is, becauſe his influxive preſence maketh heaven. That's the <hi>Ordo influxûs</hi> I mentioned, for which he is ſaid to be <hi>our God.</hi> Beſides this, there is <hi>ordo Divini cultûs,</hi> on our part, The reſpect of our being ſerviceable to him: when we love him, and fear him, and honour him, and adhere unto him as we ought. To all theſe there is bleſſedneſſe pronounced in ſeverall Pſalmes: to thoſe that <hi>fear him,</hi> Pſal. 128.1. to thoſe that <hi>keep his teſtimonies,</hi> Pſal. 119.2. to thoſe that <hi>truſt in him,</hi> Pſal. 84.12. If we take it thus, the point is this in ſumme, There is no true happineſſe, but in the worſhip and ſervice of God. <hi>Felices ſunt qui Deo vivunt,</hi> that's S. Bernards: <hi>Servire Deo eſt regnare,</hi> that's S. Ambroſe his expreſſion: As much as this, The godly man is onely the true happy man. Yet we muſt underſtand it aright: It is not to ſerve him onely in outward profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which either makes us <hi>his,</hi> or him <hi>ours.</hi> There are many who pretend to ſerve him, who cannot challenge this intereſt: for they ſerve him but with their <hi>lips;</hi> in <hi>act,</hi> themſelves and their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:156852:22"/>own pleaſures: in this both hypocrites and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that under the ſhew of one God ſet up many to themſelves. The Epicure he makes his belly his God, the laſcivious man his luſt, the voluptuous man his pleaſure, the factious man his humour, the covetous man his mammon. I name this laſt. It is the obſervation of S. Auſtin, in his 7 book <hi>De Civitate Dei,</hi> and of Lactantius in his ſecond <hi>De Origine Erroris,</hi> That avarice gives laws to religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whil'ſt generally <hi>ſub abtentu Numinis supiditas colitur.</hi> Yea, and S. Paul expreſſeth it more pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, That <hi>covetouſneſſe is idolatry,</hi> Col. 3.5. And <hi>the covetous man an idolater,</hi> Epheſ. 5.5. For he doth the ſame to his <hi>gold,</hi> that the heathen did to their <hi>idoles:</hi> he makes his gold his God; his God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his joy, and his care, and his confidence: Thoſe pictures he worſhips, though otherwiſe he abhorres idoles; to theſe he offers his ſervice, he gives them his heart, he extols them, aſcribes unto them the glory of his happineſſe: Theſe are thy gods, O Iſrael, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt: this money got thee ſuch a preferment, procured ſuch a deliverance, prevailed in ſuch a ſute. It's the ſecret idolatrie which runnes through the world. But ſuch men as theſe, they are as farre from God as from his ſervice, and as farre from happineſſe as from God. Whoſoever will make ſure of the Lord to be his God, he muſt put the idoles out of his heart, he muſt go out of himſelf, he muſt not willingly harbour any ſinne. Sinne ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates from God, excludes from happineſſe, cuts off both priviledges, of God's being ours, and our
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:156852:23"/>being God's. Yet there is one thing more; with which I will conclude: Since it is ſo, that happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is ſeated in theſe mutuall intercurrences, of calling the Lord <hi>our God,</hi> and our ſelves <hi>his people;</hi> and ſeeing religion is the <hi>Vinculum unionis,</hi> which makes theſe mutuall intereſts intercurrent, and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples them together; it follows as the upſhot of all, That the chief and choiceſt part of Nationall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe confiſts in the puritie of God's worſhip, in the enjoying of God's ordinances, in the free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Goſpel; that is, in the truth and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of religion. In this alone there are all ſweets, all beauties, all bliſſes, all glories. It is as the ark of God to Iſrael, and as the golden candleſtick to the Churches, the elevating principle which advanceth a Chriſtian Nation above the heathen, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches above other Chriſtian Nations, and this Iland in which we live (I may ſay without arrogancie) above all. There is no Nation in the world, which hath had the condition of religion ſo pure and proſperous, as we, for almoſt theſe hundred yeares. It's true, if God calls us to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, we cannot ſay that we have anſwered our op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities: we find not wherein to boaſt of our righteouſneſſe; for we are a ſinfull people, whoſe lives (for the moſt part of us) are as much worſe, as our means and profeſſions better then in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. It is true alſo, that of later yeares the love of religion in moſt hath grown cold, and the puritie by ſome hath been ſtained and corrupted: and I will not now diſcuſſe where the fault hath been; the rather, becauſe it is every mans endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:156852:23"/>it from himſelf. Onely I will adde thus much, That whereſoever the fault is, there is no man hath ſhewed himſelf more forward to reform it then the King himſelf. But Princes cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes attain their ends according to their liking, becauſe they ſee with other eyes, and execute with other hands then their own. And if we ſhould caſt the faults of men upon authoritie, we ſhould do wrong (I fear) to thoſe who do not deſerve it: for even this very yeare, notwithſtanding the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of corruptions hath been with ſo much zeal and diligence endeavoured, yet the end is not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: Nay, in ſome reſpects, it is ſo farre ſet back, that, to my underſtanding, the ſtate of religion hath never been worſe ſince the firſt reformation, then this preſent yeare: in reſpect, firſt, of the greatneſſe of our diſtractions, which have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided us all one from another: then, of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſects and ſectaries which cry indeed, as the Jews before them, <hi>Templum Domini;</hi> but with a worſe addition, <hi>ut Templum Domini diruatur.</hi> Laſtly, in reſpect of the many diſhonours done to the ſervice of God, with ſo much ſcorn and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall to religion, that in forein parts they queſtion, whether all this time we had any. No doubt all this is come upon us for our ſinnes: let us remove them, and then God will bleſſe our ſtudie of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. But yet in the mean time let us remember that meſſage, which the good Biſhop ſent to Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius, <hi>Domine, ſol ad occaſum deſcendit.</hi> Our ſun-ſhine is but yet declining; it may come to ſet, if we now begin to diſguſt this greateſt bleſſing of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:156852:24"/>religion, which God hath beſtowed upon us. Let us learn to regard it more, to love it better, to bleſſe God for <hi>it,</hi> and for <hi>his government</hi> who upholds it: a Prince ſo devout and religious in his own perſon, that if all were like him, we ſhould have a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Saints. In this reſpect, we may uſe Velleius his words of his Majeſtie, <hi>Cùm ſit imperie Maximus, exemplo Major eſt:</hi> The luſtre of his <hi>pietie</hi> ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the luſtre of his <hi>empire.</hi> If therefore that of Syneſius be true, That men generally affect to write after the copies which are ſet by their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; it behoves us all, both to take out the <hi>leſſon,</hi> and to bleſſe God for the <hi>copie.</hi> And moreover, as this day puts us in mind, let us all ſend up our moſt affectionate prayers, that his Throne may be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Righteouſneſſe, his Crown exalted with Honour, his Scepter be for <hi>power</hi> like Moſes rod, for <hi>flouriſhing</hi> like Aaron's; that his happy reigne may in <hi>himſelf</hi> outlive us all, and in <hi>his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> be perpetuated to all generations; that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ages may confeſſe, <hi>Surely God hath been fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable unto this land, and hath not dealt ſo with any Nation. O how happy are the people that are in ſuch a caſe! Yea, how happy are the people which have the Lord for their God!</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:156852:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
